const arr = [{"id":0,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following conditions is recombinant erythropoietin indicated for?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia due to chronic kidney disease","bool":true},{"option":"Anemia due to thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia due to malnutrition","bool":false}]},{"id":1,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 9-year-old boy presents to the emergency department with left-sided hemiplegia. There is no history of head trauma to explain this presentation. If he had been diagnosed with anemia a few months ago, which of the following accounts for hemiplegia?","answers":[{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Multiple myeloma","bool":false},{"option":"Fainting due to anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false}]},{"id":2,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"What is the advantage of fingerprinting?","answers":[{"option":"It enables absolute identification of an individual","bool":true},{"option":"It is applicable for all people","bool":false},{"option":"It does not require any special and expensive instruments","bool":false},{"option":"It is applicable for all age groups","bool":false},{"option":"No special training required","bool":false}]},{"id":3,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which one of the following cells is dominant in viral infection?","answers":[{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false}]},{"id":4,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 35-year-old man with a history of intravenous (IV) drug abuse has generalized lymphadenopathy. Which of the following tests would help in finding the cause of his lymphadenopathy?","answers":[{"option":"Histopathology","bool":false},{"option":"HIV serology","bool":true},{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Ultrasonography","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow biopsy","bool":false}]},{"id":5,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Putrefaction is said to be colliquative when there is which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Colour change at right iliac fossa","bool":false},{"option":"Swollen, puffy, bloated face","bool":false},{"option":"Tissue conversion into solid mass","bool":false},{"option":"Appearance of maggots","bool":true},{"option":"Distention of abdominal cavity","bool":false}]},{"id":6,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"The process of decomposition in the air is twice as rapid as in water and eight times as rapid as in the soil this is called?","answers":[{"option":"Casper's dictum","bool":true},{"option":"Fudin's principle","bool":false},{"option":"Newton law","bool":false},{"option":"Locard's exchange principle","bool":false},{"option":"Siphon principle","bool":false}]},{"id":7,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Spontaneous bleeding becomes evident when the platelet count falls below which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"60,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":false},{"option":"40,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":false},{"option":"100,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":false},{"option":"75,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":false},{"option":"20,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":true}]},{"id":8,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following is the first immediate sign after death?","answers":[{"option":"Stiffening","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary relaxation","bool":false},{"option":"Rigor mortis","bool":false},{"option":"Putrefaction","bool":false},{"option":"Primary relaxation","bool":true}]},{"id":9,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A dead body is found by a group of people near the station. It is concluded that 6 to 10 hours have passed since the time of death. Which one of the following is most likely to be developed by this time in the body?","answers":[{"option":"Postmortem caloricity","bool":false},{"option":"Potassium increase in CSF","bool":false},{"option":"Postmortem lividity","bool":true},{"option":"Instantaneous rigor","bool":false},{"option":"Rigor mortis","bool":false}]},{"id":10,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 25-year-old male presents to the clinic with easy fatigability and generalized weakness. On examination he has blood pressure (BP)=110/60 mm of Hg, looks pale, and has koilonychia. His complete blood count (CBC) shows: Hb=9.7 g/dl, MCV=69 fl, MCHC=26 g/dl. What is the most likely cause of anemia in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia major","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia minor","bool":false}]},{"id":11,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Through which of the following bones age and sex determination of a skeleton can be determined?","answers":[{"option":"Metacarpals","bool":false},{"option":"Vertebrae","bool":false},{"option":"Skull and mandible","bool":true},{"option":"Ribs","bool":false},{"option":"Radius and ulna","bool":false}]},{"id":12,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"What is the cephalic index?","answers":[{"option":"The ratio of the maximum breadth of the skull and anterioposterior length of skull","bool":true},{"option":"Maximum anteroposterior length of skull","bool":false},{"option":"Sum of the maximum breadth of the skull and the maximum length of skull","bool":false},{"option":"The maximum transverse breadth of skull","bool":false},{"option":"Superimposition technique","bool":false}]},{"id":13,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A decapitated dead body of a male is brought for autopsy. What will be the most important part of an autopsy in this case for further identification?","answers":[{"option":"Preservation of 1st vertebra of the body distal to the cut","bool":false},{"option":"Taking photographs","bool":false},{"option":"Taking bone marrow for DNA fingerprinting","bool":false},{"option":"Taking poor prints","bool":false},{"option":"Taking fingerprints of the body","bool":true}]},{"id":14,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A boy is convicted of a criminal offense and the judge of the juvenile court orders to send him to a reformatory school. This is because his age is less than which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"17 years","bool":false},{"option":"15 years","bool":false},{"option":"18 years","bool":true},{"option":"16 years","bool":false},{"option":"14 years","bool":false}]},{"id":15,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A male aged about 16-17 years is sent to confirm his age. Advisable single radiograph would be which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Elbow joint","bool":true},{"option":"Wrist joint","bool":false},{"option":"Skull","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Sternum","bool":false}]},{"id":16,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"During the exhumation of an unidentified grave, a human skeleton was recovered.  What will be the most reliable bones to determine sex?","answers":[{"option":"Femur","bool":false},{"option":"Skull and pelvis","bool":true},{"option":"Skull and femur","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Skull","bool":false}]},{"id":17,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Why is parenteral administration of folic acid not favored in patients?","answers":[{"option":"It is too painful through the parenteral route","bool":false},{"option":"It is rapidly metabolized and eliminated","bool":false},{"option":"Given orally because it is very tasty and hence the patient's compliance is very high","bool":false},{"option":"Its profound deficiency is not seen in human beings","bool":false},{"option":"It is well absorbed orally even in patients with malabsorption syndromes","bool":true}]},{"id":18,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A cord blood sample of an Rh-ve mother was sent for laboratory testing during labor. Which of the following would indicate the need for blood exchange transfusion?","answers":[{"option":"Hemoglobin = 10 mg/dL","bool":false},{"option":"Indirect coombs test is weakly negative","bool":false},{"option":"Peripheral cells shows spherocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocyte is corrected to 7%","bool":true},{"option":"Serum bilirubin = 2.5 mg/dL","bool":false}]},{"id":19,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"The postmortem sign of 'cattle trucking' is seen in which organ?","answers":[{"option":"Cornea","bool":false},{"option":"Brain","bool":false},{"option":"Limbs","bool":false},{"option":"Heart","bool":false},{"option":"Retina","bool":true}]},{"id":20,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"What is the most common cause of macrocytic anaemia?","answers":[{"option":"von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12/B9 deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin C deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic uremic syndrome","bool":false}]},{"id":21,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 20-year-old male is brought to the outpatient department with a history of painless cervical lymphadenopathy and a physician is suspecting malignancy. What is the key investigation required to get a diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Excisional biopsy of the node","bool":true},{"option":"Erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR)","bool":false},{"option":"Fine needle aspiration (FNA)","bool":false},{"option":"Chest X-ray (CXR)","bool":false}]},{"id":22,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"The age of a young boy needs to be determined. Dental X-ray reveals mixed dentition and examination of the oral cavity reveals that the first molars have erupted. What is the approximate age of this boy?","answers":[{"option":"5-7 years","bool":false},{"option":"6-7 years","bool":true},{"option":"10-12 years","bool":false},{"option":"16-18 years","bool":false},{"option":"6-9 years","bool":false}]},{"id":23,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"The approximate age of a girl needs to be determined as ordered by the court. After getting a series of X-rays done, it is revealed that she has only 3 carpal bones ossified. What is the likely age of the girl?","answers":[{"option":"10","bool":false},{"option":"3","bool":true},{"option":"1","bool":false},{"option":"7","bool":false},{"option":"6","bool":false}]},{"id":24,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 13-year-old female presents to the outpatient department (OPD) with on and off menorrhagia, bleeding gums, and petechial rashes. Her laboratory reports show the following results; Hb= 12.5 g/dl, platelet count= 350,000/mm3, activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT)= 49s (normal: 29-40s). Which of the following could be the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":false},{"option":"von Willebrand disease","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombotic microangiopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false}]},{"id":25,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 5-year-old boy comes to the outpatient department complaining of a painful and swollen knee. On examination, bleeding is seen within the knee joint but with no signs of physical trauma. His mother gives a family history of a maternal uncle who recently died of a bleeding disorder. Investigations show isolated increased APTT. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic uremic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia C","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":true}]},{"id":26,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following agents directly activates plasminogen?","answers":[{"option":"Tissue plasminogen activator (tPA)","bool":false},{"option":"Urokinase","bool":true},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false}]},{"id":27,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"In case of an injury, a deficiency of which of the following would impair the adhesion of platelets to the subendothelial collagen?","answers":[{"option":"Antithrombin III","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand factor","bool":true},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinogen stabilizing factor","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmin","bool":false}]},{"id":28,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Where will hypostasis be seen in a body drowned in running water?","answers":[{"option":"No lividity will be seen","bool":true},{"option":"Front of the nose","bool":false},{"option":"Dependant part of upper limbs","bool":false},{"option":"Lower limbs","bool":false},{"option":"Back of the body","bool":false}]},{"id":29,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following genotypes correctly correspond to the silent carrier state of alpha thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"α α/α –","bool":true},{"option":"α –/α –","bool":false},{"option":"αα/αα","bool":false},{"option":"α α/– –","bool":false},{"option":"– –/– α","bool":false}]},{"id":30,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A dead body is brought to the mortuary for post mortem examination. The post-mortem rigidity is present throughout the body from head to toe. What is the estimated time of death?","answers":[{"option":"12-24 hours","bool":true},{"option":"4-18 hours","bool":false},{"option":"2-4 hours","bool":false},{"option":"24-36 hours","bool":false},{"option":"36-48 hours","bool":false}]},{"id":31,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A dead body is brought in for post mortem examination and according to an eye witness, the death occurred 6-8 hours ago. Which of these signs will confirm the witness's account?","answers":[{"option":"Fully developed but fixed lividity","bool":true},{"option":"Rigor mortis in the entire body","bool":false},{"option":"Blister development under the skin","bool":false},{"option":"Greenish discoloration of the right flank","bool":false},{"option":"Fully developed but not fixed lividity","bool":false}]},{"id":32,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which transfusion product of blood carries the highest risk of bacterial contamination?","answers":[{"option":"Cryoprecipitate","bool":false},{"option":"Whole blood","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Packed red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":true}]},{"id":33,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following white blood cells produce the major basic protein?","answers":[{"option":"Megakaryocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":true},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false}]},{"id":34,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"The age of a young boy needs to be determined. Dental X-ray reveals mixed dentition and an examination of the oral cavity reveals that the first and second molars have erupted. What is the approximate age of this boy?","answers":[{"option":"10 years","bool":false},{"option":"12 to 13 years","bool":true},{"option":"6 to 7 years","bool":false},{"option":"10 to 12 years","bool":false},{"option":"8 to 9 years","bool":false}]},{"id":35,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which one of the following is not one of the reasons why oral iron gluconate is not preferred?","answers":[{"option":"Metallic taste","bool":true},{"option":"Upset GIT","bool":false},{"option":"Black stools","bool":false},{"option":"Abdominal pain","bool":false},{"option":"Vomiting","bool":false}]},{"id":36,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 32-year-old woman has given birth to a stillborn hydropic baby with hepatosplenomegaly. What will be seen in her hemoglobin electrophoresis?","answers":[{"option":"HbF","bool":false},{"option":"HbH","bool":false},{"option":"HbS","bool":false},{"option":"Hb Barts","bool":true},{"option":"HbA2","bool":false}]},{"id":37,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A body is recovered from a densely populated neighborhood. The body is in an advanced stage of putrefaction, with greenish discoloration of the skin, distention of the abdomen, and muscle rigidity. Which of the following is the cause of rigidity in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Heat stiffening","bool":false},{"option":"Instantaneous rigor","bool":false},{"option":"Cold stiffening","bool":false},{"option":"Rigor mortis","bool":false},{"option":"Gas stiffening","bool":true}]},{"id":38,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A girl is brought to the outpatient department with complaints of gum bleeding, and epistaxis. Her complete blood count (CBC) shows a normal platelet count and prolonged bleeding time. There is a family history of a younger sister with easy bruising. What is the diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":true},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":false},{"option":"Drug induced thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K deficiency","bool":false}]},{"id":39,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"An 18-year-old female patient was brought to the outpatient department with a complaint of on-and-off fever for 6 months and lymphadenopathy. On biopsy, a diagnosis of Hodgkin lymphoma was made. Which of the following cells are the characteristic diagnostic cell in Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Reed sternberg cells","bool":true},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false}]},{"id":40,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 32-year-old male came to the outpatient department complaining of fever, fatigue, weakness, weight loss, and night sweats. His blood report shows Hb: 9mg/dl, WBC: 82x 10E9, and platelets: 84x 10E9. Peripheral film review showed 69% blast cells. The patient was advised of bone marrow aspirate, trephine biopsy, and cytogenetics testing. In leukemic presentations, one of the following cells replaces the normal bone marrow cells to make it hypercellular?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Erythrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Blast cells","bool":true},{"option":"Metamyelocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Myelocytes","bool":false}]},{"id":41,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 72-year-old male came to the outpatient department complaining of fever, fatigue, weakness, weight loss, and night sweats. His blood report shows Hb: 8 mg/dl, WBC: 3.5 x 10E9, and platelets: 90 x 10E9. Peripheral film review showed dysplastic neutrophils. The patient was advised of bone marrow aspirate, trephine biopsy, and cytogenetics testing. Which of the following is not the morphological feature of dysplastic syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"More than 20% blast cells","bool":true},{"option":"Pseudo-Pegler-Huet cells","bool":false},{"option":"Nuclear budding abnormalities","bool":false},{"option":"Ring sideroblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastoid maturation","bool":false}]},{"id":42,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"which of the following cell types is a precursor to platelets?","answers":[{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Megakaryocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Histiocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Erythroid precursors","bool":false},{"option":"Myeloid precursors","bool":false}]},{"id":43,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 25-year-old female patient comes to the outpatient department with a history of easy bruising and prolonged bleeding after a minor cut. Upon history, she also told the doctor that her siblings have a similar problem. What are the initial tests that should be done to screen for bleeding disorders?","answers":[{"option":"Complete blood count, Fibrinogen, PT, APTT","bool":true},{"option":"Bleeding time, factor assay, bone trephine","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count, bleeding time, factor VIII level.","bool":false},{"option":"Bleeding time, complete blood count, PT/APTT","bool":false},{"option":"Factor assay, complete blood count, thrombin time","bool":false}]},{"id":44,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following hormone is produced by the liver for the synthesis of platelets from megakaryocytes?","answers":[{"option":"Thyroxin","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombopoietin","bool":true},{"option":"Erythropoitin","bool":false},{"option":"Corticosteroids","bool":false},{"option":"Growth hormone","bool":false}]},{"id":45,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following enzymes is regulated by hepcidin?","answers":[{"option":"Hephaestin","bool":false},{"option":"Duodenal cytochrome","bool":false},{"option":"Divalent metal transporter","bool":false},{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Ferroportin","bool":true}]},{"id":46,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 15-year-old female, diagnosed with hereditary spherocytosis for 2 years, came to the outpatient department complaining of shortness of breath and bleeding from gum. Her hemoglobin is 6.6 g/ dl, her white blood count is 1.2x 10E9/l and her platelet count is 30 x10E9. Peripheral smear shows pancytopenia and reticulocytopenia. Which of the following complications must she have developed in relation to the problems mentioned above?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic crisis","bool":true},{"option":"G6PD defeciency","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Gall stones","bool":false}]},{"id":47,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 6-year-old girl is evaluated for anemia. Her blood report shows hemoglobin of 5g/dl with 7% reticulocyte. Her platelets and leukocytes are normal. Peripheral smear shows numerous spherocytes. Her physical examination revealed splenomegaly. Her mother also has a similar history. Based on the information given above, what diagnosis can we make?","answers":[{"option":"G6PD defeciency","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombosis with thrombocytopenia syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Hereitary spherocytosis","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic uremic syndrome","bool":false}]},{"id":48,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which one of the following is a cause of inherited aplastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Fanconi anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Cytomegalovirus","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Immune mediated aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Epstein bar virus","bool":false}]},{"id":49,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Iron is delivered to body tissues bound to which of the following molecules?","answers":[{"option":"Transferrin","bool":true},{"option":"Hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Hepcidin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemosiderin","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin","bool":false}]},{"id":50,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A patient is receiving heparin by continuous intravenous infusion. The doctor is most likely to ask the nurse to monitor which of the following symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Tinnitus","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased blood pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Vomiting","bool":false},{"option":"Gum bleeding","bool":true},{"option":"Deacreased pulse rate","bool":false}]},{"id":51,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A patient is on antiplatelet therapy and is about to undergo surgery, His doctor advised him to discontinue the antiplatelet and wait at least one week before undergoing the surgery. Which of the following drugs is the patient most likely taking?","answers":[{"option":"dipyridamole","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":true},{"option":"Amciximab","bool":false},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":false},{"option":"Cilostazol","bool":false}]},{"id":52,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following drugs directly binds to fibrin clots leading to breakdown of plasminogen?","answers":[{"option":"Fondaparinux","bool":false},{"option":"Desirudin","bool":false},{"option":"Alteplase (tPA)","bool":true},{"option":"Dabigatran","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false}]},{"id":53,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 2-year-old boy is brought to the outpatient department with the complaint of easy bruising all over the body for the past one year. He has no history of trauma. His right knee joint is now swollen. Lab reports show normal platelets, normal prothrombin time, Hb of 10 g/ dl. APTT is raised. What further investigation is required to confirm diagnosis.","answers":[{"option":"Factor V levels","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand factor","bool":false},{"option":"Factor X levels","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VIII levels","bool":true},{"option":"Factor II levels","bool":false}]},{"id":54,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 5-year-old girl is brought to the outpatient department with the complaint of recurrent episodes of epistaxis and gingival bleeding. On examination, she is pale and has bruise marks all over her body. Her lab reports show normal PT/ APTT, normal platelet count, and normal Hb levels in her body but her bleeding time is prolonged. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Von willebrand disease","bool":true},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia B","bool":false}]},{"id":55,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 10-year-old boy is brought to the emergency department with a complaint of fever and loose motion for the last 10 days. He has developed bruises all over his body since last night and is bleeding rectally. On examination, he is sick-looking with cold peripheries. His lab reports show delayed capillary refill with decreased platelets, prolonged prothrombin time, activated partial thromboplastin time, and raised D-dimers. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulopathy","bool":true},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand's disease","bool":false},{"option":"Dysentery","bool":false}]},{"id":56,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 3-year-old boy is brought to the outpatient department with the complaint of bruises all over his body for the past 2 days. He is otherwise active and playful. Physical examination is unremarkable. Complete blood count shows the total count of platelet at 20,000. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Disseminated Intravascular coagulopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand's disease","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet function disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":true},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false}]},{"id":57,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 15-months old baby is brought to the clinic with the complaint of progressive pallor and edema all over his body. He has a history of loose motions 1 week back. The mother also complains that her child is passing less urine than normal. examinations show edema and anemia. Lab reports indicate hemoglobin of 6g/dl, platelets of 90,000, and increased levels of urea and creatinine in the blood. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Nephrotic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic uremic syndrome","bool":true}]},{"id":58,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A nine-month-old baby presented to the outpatient department with a complaint of progressive pallor and failure to thrive for the past 4 months, his parents are first cousins. On examination, the baby is underweight at 5.6 kg, severely anemic, with mild jaundice, and hepatosplenomegaly. Complete blood count indicates Hb= 5.2 g/dl, MCV= 65 fl, Hb-f= 85%, and TLC and platelets are normal. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Beta thalassemia major","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Beta thalassemia trait","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":59,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 6-year-old boy develops sudden pallor and jaundice. He has taken fava beans. His Hb is 3.5 g/dl with normal TLC and platelets. Total bilirubin was 5 mg/dl, predominantly unconjugated and the reticulocyte count is > 20 hps. Urine is also positive for Hb. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Malaria","bool":false},{"option":"G6PD defeciency","bool":true},{"option":"Beta thalassemia major","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":60,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following indicates the earliest changes that occur in eyes after death?","answers":[{"option":"Sunken eye balls","bool":false},{"option":"dilated pupil","bool":false},{"option":"Loss of reflexes","bool":true},{"option":"Tache noirs spots","bool":false},{"option":"Segmentation of retinal vessels","bool":false}]},{"id":61,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A dying patient consented to a viscera transplantation after his death. When can a doctor take out the viscera for transplantation?","answers":[{"option":"On absent breath sounds","bool":false},{"option":"when ECG gets flat","bool":false},{"option":"After systemic death","bool":false},{"option":"After molecular death","bool":false},{"option":"After brain stem death","bool":true}]},{"id":62,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A child of pubertal age alleged to have been sexually assaulted was brought to the M/L section to determine the age. Which one of the following can be the best site for the X-ray to determine age.","answers":[{"option":"Shin","bool":false},{"option":"Foot and ankle","bool":false},{"option":"Knee","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Hands and Wrist","bool":true}]},{"id":63,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"The body of a 35-year-old was brought for autopsy, his relatives give a history of a tattoo, which was not found during the autopsy. Which of the following should be directed to find the tattoo ink?","answers":[{"option":"Lymph nodes","bool":true},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Thyroid","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false}]},{"id":64,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"\"Chilotic line\" is a mathematical index which helps in determination of which of the following factors?","answers":[{"option":"Sex","bool":true},{"option":"Race","bool":false},{"option":"Age","bool":false},{"option":"Height","bool":false},{"option":"Stature","bool":false}]},{"id":65,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A young male is brought to emergency with the complaint of yellow discoloration of the sclera, after taking trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole that some general physician prescribed for some infection, the details of which are unknown. Laboratory reports show Hb of 8.5 g/dl, normal platelets, and TLC, total bilirubin is 4.2 mg/dl with predominant indirect hyperbilirubinemia. Liver enzymes are normal. The patient gives a previous history of recurring episodic jaundice and lethargy in the past. The given explanation best corresponds to which one of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase defeciency","bool":false},{"option":"Cold agglutinin disease","bool":false},{"option":"Paroxymal nocturnal hemoglobinurea","bool":false},{"option":"Drug induced hemolytic anemia","bool":true}]},{"id":66,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A young female presented to the outpatient department with sudden onset of abdominal distention for 1 week. On examination, there is a  fluid thrill, palmer erythema, and bilateral edema. Doppler ultrasound shows hepatic vein and inferior vena cava thrombosis. The thrombophilic profile shows a deficiency of proteins C and S. How long should we anticoagulate this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Life long","bool":false},{"option":"3 months","bool":false},{"option":"6 years","bool":false},{"option":"6 months","bool":true},{"option":"1 year","bool":false}]},{"id":67,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 28-year-old male gave a history of laparotomy due to intestinal perforation 1 month back, his mobility was reduced due to this condition and now he has developed right leg swelling and pain up to mid-thigh for the last 1 week which is progressing gradually. What will be the duration of anticoagulation in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"3 months","bool":true},{"option":"6 years","bool":false},{"option":"Life long","bool":false},{"option":"12 months","bool":false},{"option":"1 year","bool":false}]},{"id":68,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 36-year-old female with no known comorbidity comes to the outpatient department with a complaint of progressive right leg swelling, pain, and redness for the past 15 days. She also has a history of multiple 2nd-trimester miscarriages. What is the most probable diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Vasculitis","bool":false},{"option":"Conecctive tissue disease","bool":false},{"option":"Anti thrombin III defeciency","bool":false},{"option":"Antiphospholipid antibody syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Deep vein thrombosis","bool":false}]},{"id":69,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 30-year-old female with no known comorbidity comes to the outpatient department with a complaint of left lower limb swelling and redness for the last 15 days. She gives a history of multiple second-trimester miscarriages. What is the investigation of choice for this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Complete blood count","bool":false},{"option":"X-ray knee","bool":false},{"option":"Doppler ultrasound of left leg","bool":true},{"option":"Ultrasound pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"D-dimer","bool":false}]},{"id":70,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 38-year-old female comes to the outpatient department with the complaint of easy bruisability, gum bleeding, and menorrhagia. The examination was unremarkable except for pallor. Lab reports show Hb at 6.5 g/dl, Total leukocyte count at 7.8/ cmm, and platelet count at 10,000 cmm, also reports are negative for antinuclear antibodies. Which of the following can be diagnosis for this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Connective tissue disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic liver disease","bool":false}]},{"id":71,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following is the most correct statement regarding an allograft?","answers":[{"option":"A graft performed between different species","bool":false},{"option":"An organ or tissue transplanted from one individual to another","bool":true},{"option":"A graft placed in its normal position","bool":false},{"option":"A graft taken from the same individual","bool":false},{"option":"A graft placed in a site different from that where the organ is normally located","bool":false}]},{"id":72,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 60-year-old patient with a history of hypertension and hyperlipidemia presents with fatigue, weight loss, and night sweats. Further evaluation reveals a high white blood cell count and splenomegaly. A diagnosis of myeloproliferative disorder is made. What is the drug of choice for the management of this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Ruxolitinib","bool":true},{"option":"Rituximab","bool":false},{"option":"Etanercept","bool":false},{"option":"Imatinib","bool":false}]},{"id":73,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"What is the first-line treatment option for immune thrombocytopenic purpura?","answers":[{"option":"RhD immunoglobulin","bool":false},{"option":"Fostamatinib","bool":false},{"option":"Steroids","bool":true},{"option":"Eltrombopag","bool":false},{"option":"Splenectomy","bool":false}]},{"id":74,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 24-year-old male presents to the emergency with a new-onset blurring of vision with mild drooping of the eyelid. He reports being bitten by a snake in his village a few hours ago for which he only used a tourniquet and sucked out the venom. Which snakebite can lead to such a presentation?","answers":[{"option":"Cobra","bool":true},{"option":"Python","bool":false},{"option":"Copperhead","bool":false},{"option":"Anaconda","bool":false},{"option":"Cottonmouth","bool":false}]},{"id":75,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which one of these is the single best test for the diagnosis of polycythemia vera?","answers":[{"option":"JAK 2 mutation","bool":true},{"option":"Radiochromium labelled RBCs","bool":false},{"option":"Serum erythropoeitin","bool":false},{"option":"Serum LDH","bool":false},{"option":"Serum iron studies","bool":false}]},{"id":76,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 34-year-old woman presents to the office after a positive pregnancy test. Her last pregnancy was 8 years ago, which was a miscarriage. She is diagnosed case of APLA syndrome. Which of these is the best management option for her current pregnancy?","answers":[{"option":"Aspirin alone","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin alone","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin+warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin alone","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin+heparin","bool":true}]},{"id":77,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 33-year-old male presents to the emergency with the complaint of palpitations for the last few hours. Arrival EKG reveals atrial fibrillation with rapid ventricular rate. IV esmolol is administered and the patient achieves a normal heart rate. The hemodynamics are stable, and a transesophageal echocardiogram reveals no thrombus in the left atrium. Which of these is the next best step in management?","answers":[{"option":"IV verapamil","bool":false},{"option":"Defibrillation","bool":false},{"option":"Anticoagulation with heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Repeat beta blocker","bool":false},{"option":"DC cardioversion","bool":true}]},{"id":78,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"An 8-year-old male presents to the clinic with a history of recurrent episodes of abdominal pain, joint pain, and skin rashes. He also reports frequent episodes of fever and blood in the urine. The patient's mother says that these symptoms have been occurring for several months and have been getting worse over time.\r\n\r\nUpon examination, the patient is found to have joint pain and stiffness in his knees, ankles, and wrists. He also has a diffuse, non-pruritic rash on his lower legs and feet. The patient's abdomen is mildly tender to palpation, and he has difficulty standing and walking due to pain and stiffness in his joints. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"IgA nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Post streptococcal glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Henoch Schonlein purpura","bool":true},{"option":"Microscopic polyangitis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false}]},{"id":79,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which one of these disorders are characterized by the presence of 'smudge cells' in the peripheral smear?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic myeloblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myeloblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Myeloproliferative neoplasms","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia","bool":true}]},{"id":80,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 25-year-old man presents to the emergency department after being bitten by a snake while hiking. He reports severe pain and swelling at the site of the bite, as well as nausea, vomiting, and difficulty breathing. Physical examination reveals a puncture wound on his left ankle which is constantly oozing out blood, as well as significant edema and ecchymosis in the surrounding area. The patient's blood pressure is low and his heart rate is elevated. Lab counts reveal thrombocytopenia. What is the management of choice for this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Prazosin","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet transfusion","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-Snake venom","bool":true},{"option":"Tetanus toxoid","bool":false}]},{"id":81,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"What is the investigation of choice for Von Willebrand disease?","answers":[{"option":"D-dimer levels","bool":false},{"option":"Serum ESR","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet count","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count","bool":false},{"option":"Ristocetin cofactor assay","bool":true}]},{"id":82,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"What is the best treatment regimen for Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"IAP","bool":false},{"option":"CDDP","bool":false},{"option":"ECF","bool":false},{"option":"ABVD regimen","bool":true},{"option":"CHOP regimen","bool":false}]},{"id":83,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 25-year-old man was rushed to the emergency department after an accidental fall from a motorbike. He was bleeding profusely and was examined for possible fractures and his x-ray report shows a fracture of the femur and the tibia. What kind of anemia is he at risk of?","answers":[{"option":"Normochromic and microcytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypochromic and microcytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypochromic and macrocytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypochromic and normocytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Normochromic normocytic anemia","bool":true}]},{"id":84,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"An old bedridden patient, who was diagnosed with deep vein thrombosis and had been prescribed warfarin as an anticoagulant for her condition a few years ago, was reported to the outpatient department with abnormally prolonged bleeding from the nose. She was given vitamin K as an antidote. What monitoring parameters are important to keep warfarin activity in check?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombin time","bool":false},{"option":"Aptt","bool":false},{"option":"Muscle enzymes and blood pressure","bool":false},{"option":"PT/ INR","bool":true},{"option":"Clotting time","bool":false}]},{"id":85,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Two students were studying a case of a 40-year-old male patient with complaints of burning stomach pain relieved by taking food. He was diagnosed with peptic ulcer and was found to be anemic. His tests showed high ferritin levels along with high iron absorption. After medication, his iron absorption decreased. Which factor is synthesized by the liver and is responsible for regulating iron absorption by binding to ferroportin?","answers":[{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Iron Responsive element","bool":false},{"option":"Hepcidin","bool":true},{"option":"Divalent metal transporter-1","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false}]},{"id":86,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which cells can perform multiple phagocytic events and remain functional for months?","answers":[{"option":"T lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"B lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":true},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false}]},{"id":87,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A body of a person whose epidermis got burnt was brought to the forensic department for identification. Which of the following methods is the most feasible one?","answers":[{"option":"Go for DNA samplig","bool":false},{"option":"Sample can not be collected","bool":false},{"option":"Take fingerprints as dermis is not burnt","bool":true},{"option":"Take a teeth imprint","bool":false},{"option":"Collect burnt skin and take its print","bool":false}]},{"id":88,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 45-year-old woman presented to the emergency department with acute diarrhea and abdominal discomfort for 2 weeks. Stool culture shows parasitic eggs. Which cells would be raised in complete blood count?","answers":[{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":true},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"B-lymphocytes","bool":false}]},{"id":89,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A detective is searching for evidence at a crime scene when he encounters fingerprints on the doorknob. He takes the impressions for examination. Inspection reveals a pattern in which ridges run from left to right. What is the most likely fingerprint pattern in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Arch","bool":true},{"option":"Composite","bool":false},{"option":"Floral","bool":false},{"option":"Loop","bool":false},{"option":"Whorl","bool":false}]},{"id":90,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 24-year-old male met a psychologist at the airport. While discussing his life with the psychologist, he told him that he failed entrance exam tests multiple times as he has to work part-time jobs to support himself and his family because his father was on bed rest after a leg fracture. He appeared to be very hopeful that he will pass this time as his father has now started earning again and he got a lot of time to study for the upcoming exam. This case falls under what type of behavioral model?","answers":[{"option":"Dynamism","bool":false},{"option":"Occupational efficacy","bool":false},{"option":"Optimization","bool":true},{"option":"Social responsibility","bool":false},{"option":"Personal contentment","bool":false}]},{"id":91,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"What is the term used for different psychological mechanisms which are used to endure the challenges of life and result in acquiring and maintaining a state of health and normality?","answers":[{"option":"Control systems","bool":false},{"option":"Static health models","bool":false},{"option":"Defense mechanisms","bool":true},{"option":"Immune systems","bool":false},{"option":"Dynamic roles","bool":false}]},{"id":92,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 16-year-old boy presents to the emergency department with the complaint of swelling of the right knee joint after trivial trauma. History is significant for similar incidences over the past 4 years. Their family history is positive for a bleeding disorder. Investigations show hemoglobin - 10 g/dL, white cell count - 5,000/uL, and platelets - 200,000/uL. Which of the following correctly describes the above-mentioned condition? (prothrombin time=pt, active partial thrombin time= aptt )","answers":[{"option":"Normal pt prolonged, prolonged aptt , corrects on mixing","bool":true},{"option":"Prolonged pt, normal aptt, corrects on mixing","bool":false},{"option":"Prolonged pt, normal aptt, no correction on mixing","bool":false},{"option":"Normal pt, normal appt, no need to mix","bool":false},{"option":"Prolonged pt, prolonged aptt, no correction on mixing","bool":false}]},{"id":93,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 24-year-old male presents to the office with an enlarging lump on his neck. Lymph node biopsy reveals lymphocytic infiltration in the germinal center along with tingible body macrophages in a 'starry sky' appearance. The tumor exhibits a high mitotic index and Immunohistochemistry revealed t(8:14) translocation. What virus is present in almost all ⅙ cases?","answers":[{"option":"Human immunodefeciency virus","bool":false},{"option":"Epstein barr virus (EBV)","bool":true},{"option":"Influenza virus","bool":false},{"option":"Cytomegalovirus","bool":false},{"option":"Human herpes virus","bool":false}]},{"id":94,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 12-year-old girl was brought to the emergency department with complaints of continuous nose bleeding for one hour. On examination, she was afebrile and well. The general physical examination was unremarkable. She had no history except a self-limiting viral flu a few weeks back. What is the most appropriate diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic immune thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Dengue","bool":false},{"option":"Acute immune thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":95,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A patient presented with lymphadenopathy to the clinic. A lymph node biopsy showed small lymphoid cells having a nodular appearance with prominent nucleoli. The cells were found to be CD5+ and Tdt negative. Further workup revealed (11:14) translocation. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Follicular lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Mantle zone lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Diffuse large B-cell lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Burkitt lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Marginal zone lymphoma","bool":false}]},{"id":96,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 25-year-old patient came to the outpatient department for her antenatal checkup. On examination she was pale. A complete blood picture reveals Hb 9 gm/dl with a hypochromic, microcytic picture. Which of the following statements is correct regarding the condition she is having?","answers":[{"option":"Screen for thalassemia trait","bool":false},{"option":"Investigate blood loss","bool":false},{"option":"Check for dietary habits","bool":true},{"option":"Order hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":false},{"option":"Check for family history of similar disease","bool":false}]},{"id":97,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 50-year-old male has a flight to the USA and has started experiencing sudden pain in his left calf. What is the appropriate initial management?","answers":[{"option":"Ascard 75 mg tablets","bool":false},{"option":"Subcutaneous low molecular weight heparin","bool":true},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior vena cava filter","bool":false},{"option":"DVT stocking","bool":false}]},{"id":98,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A man took anti-malarial prophylaxis before going to West Africa. Two to three weeks later he developed severe anemia along with hemoglobinuria. Which of the following is the correct statement regarding this condition?","answers":[{"option":"This disease is transferred by mosquitoes","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary disease common in females","bool":false},{"option":"This disease develops from a spontanueous mutation","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary disease common in males","bool":true},{"option":"This disease is endemic in West Africa","bool":false}]},{"id":99,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which one of the following diseases is associated with the deficiency of ADAMTS13?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP)","bool":true},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":100,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following will not be seen in case of multiple myeloma?","answers":[{"option":"Lytic bone lesions","bool":false},{"option":"Cast in urine and pus cells","bool":true},{"option":"Susceptibility to infection","bool":false},{"option":"Rouleux formation","bool":false},{"option":"Light chains excreted in urine","bool":false}]},{"id":101,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which one of the following statements is true for enoxaparin as compared to the rest of the low molecular weight heparins?","answers":[{"option":"APTT needs not to be monitored","bool":false},{"option":"Causes thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Less teratogenic","bool":false},{"option":"Can be administered intravenously in the treatment of MI","bool":true},{"option":"Short action of duration","bool":false}]},{"id":102,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A lady presented to the outpatient department complaining of fatigue, shortness of breath, and a pale face. She got diagnosed with the case of malabsorption and megaloblastic anemia. Her reports show increased MCV. Antibodies against which of the following could be a reason for her anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Alpha cells of pancreas","bool":false},{"option":"Enterocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Chief cells of gastric mucosa","bool":false},{"option":"Intrinsic factor","bool":true},{"option":"Gliadin","bool":false}]},{"id":103,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 20-year-old man is rushed to the emergency department after getting into a severe bike accident. He needs a blood transfusion immediately as he suffered from severe blood loss. Which blood group is considered a universal donor?","answers":[{"option":"O negative","bool":true},{"option":"B positive","bool":false},{"option":"AB positive","bool":false},{"option":"O positive","bool":false},{"option":"AB negative","bool":false}]},{"id":104,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following cells are seen in megaloblastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Hyposegmented neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Hyper segmented polymorphonuclear leukocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Activated mast cells","bool":false},{"option":"Micro ovalocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Nucleated red blood cells","bool":false}]},{"id":105,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following correctly states the cause of megaloblastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Caused by the deficiency of vitamin B6 and folic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Caused by the combined deficiency of vitamin B12 and folic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Caused by the deficiency of vitamin B12 only","bool":false},{"option":"Caused by the deficiency of folic acid only","bool":false},{"option":"Caused by the deficiency of either vitamin B12 or folic acid","bool":true}]},{"id":106,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A man has an enlarged prostate gland which is palpable on digital rectal examination. He is diagnosed with prostatic adenocarcinoma and presents with anemia and pancytopenia. MCV is normal. Which of the following is the type of anemia seen in this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Myelophthisic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":true},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":107,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 6-year-old child has been diagnosed with hereditary spherocytosis and complained of an increased frequency of blood transfusions. Blood complete picture shows Hb = 6.5 gm/dL, reticulocyte count = 20%, TLC = 4000/mm³, platelets = 100,000/mm³. What will be the most appropriate treatment in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Corticosteroids with anti thymhocytic globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Splenectomy","bool":true},{"option":"Bone marrow transplant","bool":false},{"option":"Repeated transfusions with iron chelation","bool":false},{"option":"Hydroxyurea","bool":false}]},{"id":108,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A patient presented to the outpatient department with pallor and cyanosis of extremities. The doctor suspected him of a case of hemolysis and ordered investigations. He had both direct and indirect coomb test positive but only at 4°C and not at 37°C. Which of the following is the type of immunoglobulin responsible?","answers":[{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":true},{"option":"IgE","bool":false},{"option":"Both IgG and IgM","bool":false}]},{"id":109,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 77-year-old woman notices that petechiae appeared on the skin of her arms and legs over the past 3 weeks. On physical examination, she is afebrile and has no organomegaly. Laboratory studies show a normal prothrombin time and partial thromboplastin time. CBC shows hemoglobin of 12.7 g/dL, hematocrit of 37.2%, MCV of 80 μm3, platelet count of 276,000/mm3, and WBC count of 5600/mm3. Platelet function studies and fibrinogen levels are normal, and no fibrin split products are detectable. Which of the following best explains these findings?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic renal failure","bool":false},{"option":"Macronodular cirrhosis","bool":false},{"option":"Meningococcemia","bool":false},{"option":"Metastatic carcinoma","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C deficiency","bool":true}]},{"id":110,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A clinical study of patients who inherit mutations that reduce the level of ankyrin, the principal binding site for spectrin, in the RBC membrane cytoskeleton shows an increased \r\nprevalence of chronic anemia with splenomegaly. For many patients, it is observed that splenectomy reduces the severity of anemia. This beneficial effect of splenectomy is most likely related to which of the following processes?","answers":[{"option":"Decrease in opsonization of RBCs and lysis in spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in deformability of RBCs within splenic sinusoids","bool":false},{"option":"Decrease in production of reactive oxygen species by splenic macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in splenic storage of iron","bool":false},{"option":"Decrease in splenic RBC sequestration and lysis","bool":true}]},{"id":111,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"Which of the following terms is used for over production of abnormal white blood cells?","answers":[{"option":"Leucopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia vera","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":true}]},{"id":112,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 16-year-old girl has had frequent nosebleeds since childhood. Her gums bleed easily, even with routine tooth brushing. She has experienced menorrhagia since menarche at the age of 13 years. On physical examination, there are no abnormal findings. Laboratory studies show hemoglobin, 14.1 g/dL; hematocrit, 42.5%; MCV, 90 μm3; platelet count, 277,400/mm3; and WBC count, 5920/mm3. Her platelets fail to aggregate in response to ADP, collagen, epinephrine, and thrombin. The ristocetin agglutination test result is normal. There is a deficiency of glycoprotein IIb/IIIa. Prothrombin time is 12 seconds, and partial thromboplastin time is 28 seconds.  What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin C deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation","bool":false}]},{"id":113,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 10-year-old child has experienced multiple episodes of pneumonia and meningitis with septicemia since infancy. Causative organisms include Streptococcus pneumoniae and Haemophilus influenzae. On physical examination, the child has no organomegaly and no deformities. Laboratory studies show hemoglobin of 9.2 g/dL, hematocrit of 27.8%, platelet count of 372,000/mm3, and WBC count of 10,300/mm3. Hemoglobin electrophoresis shows 1% hemoglobin A2, 7% hemoglobin F, and 92% hemoglobin S. Which of the following is the most likely cause of repeated infections in this child?","answers":[{"option":"Diminished hepatic synthesis of complement proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Impaired neutrophil production","bool":false},{"option":"Absent endothelial cell expression of adhesion molecules","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced synthesis of immunoglobulins","bool":false},{"option":"Loss of normal splenic function due to recurrent ischemic injury","bool":true}]},{"id":114,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A child had a history of typhoid fever for 15 days. He was given a number of antibiotics including chloramphenicol and antipyretics. His laboratory work shows neutropenia. What is the cause of the neutropenia?","answers":[{"option":"Autoimmune destruction","bool":false},{"option":"Overwhelming fungal infection","bool":false},{"option":"Splenomegaly sequestration","bool":false},{"option":"Drug induced neutropenia","bool":true},{"option":"Immunological mediated injury due to Systemic lupus erythmatosis","bool":false}]},{"id":115,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"An 11-year-old child has a history of easy bruising.  Since the age of 9 years, he experienced hemorrhaging around the pharynx that produced acute airway obstruction. Family history indicates that other male relatives have similar bleeding problems. Laboratory studies show hemoglobin, 13.1 g/dL; hematocrit, 39.2% (N= 40-54%); platelet count, 228,000/mm3; WBC count, 5950/mm3; prothrombin time, 13 seconds (N=12-14.8s); and partial thromboplastin time is 52 seconds (27-41s). A dilution of the patient’s plasma with normal pooled plasma corrects the partial thromboplastin time. Which of the following manifestations of this illness will most likely ensue without recombinant factor VIII therapy?","answers":[{"option":"Splenomegaly","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolysis","bool":false},{"option":"Hemarthroses","bool":true},{"option":"Conjunctival petechiae","bool":false},{"option":"Hemochromatosis","bool":false}]},{"id":116,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A young girl who is suffering from Epstein Barr viral disease has a positive Monospot test. What kind of immunoglobulins are these heterophile antibodies seen in this case?","answers":[{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":true},{"option":"IgE","bool":false}]},{"id":117,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A dead body is brought to the mortuary, lower limbs are stiff, while the abdomen, chest, and upper body are relaxed. How much time has passed since death?","answers":[{"option":"12-24 hours","bool":false},{"option":"8-12 hours","bool":false},{"option":"4-8 hours","bool":false},{"option":"48-56 hours","bool":false},{"option":"36-48 hours","bool":true}]},{"id":118,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 62-year-old man has experienced vague abdominal discomfort accompanied by bloating and diarrhea for the past 6 months. On physical examination, there is a midabdominal firm mass. The stool is positive for occult blood. An abdominal CT scan shows a mass that was removed. Microscopically, the mass is composed of sheets of large lymphoid cells with large nuclei, prominent nucleoli, and frequent mitotic figures. The neoplastic cells mark with CD19+ and CD20+ and have the BCL6 gene rearrangement. Which of the following prognostic features are most applicable to this case?","answers":[{"option":"Indolent, survival of 7 to 9 years without treatment","bool":false},{"option":"Indolent, can be cured by chemotherapy","bool":false},{"option":"Indolent, often undergoes spontaneous remission","bool":false},{"option":"Aggressive, can be cured by chemotherapy","bool":true},{"option":"Aggressive, often transforms to acute leukemia","bool":false}]},{"id":119,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 55-year-old man felt a lump near his shoulder 1 week ago. On physical examination, there is an enlarged, non-tender, supraclavicular lymph node and an enlargement of the Waldeyer ring of oropharyngeal lymphoid tissue. There is no hepatosplenomegaly. CBC is normal except for findings of mild anemia. A lymph node biopsy specimen shows replacement by a monomorphous population of lymphoid cells that are twice the size of normal lymphocytes, with enlarged nuclei and prominent nucleoli. Immunohistochemical staining and flow cytometry of the node indicates that most lymphoid cells are CD19+, CD10+, CD3−, CD15−, and terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase negative (TdT−). A BCL6 gene mutation is present. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic lymphadenitis","bool":false},{"option":"Diffuse large B-cell lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Small lymphocytic lymphoma","bool":false}]},{"id":120,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 9-year-old boy has had increasing pain and swelling on the right side of his face over the past 8 months. On physical examination, there is a large, non-tender mass involving the mandible, which deforms the right side of his face. There is no lymphadenopathy or splenomegaly, and he is afebrile. A biopsy of the mass is performed and microscopic examination shows intermediate-sized lymphocytes with a high mitotic rate. A chromosome analysis shows a t(8;14) karyotype in these cells. The hemoglobin concentration is 13.2 g/dL, the platelet count is 272,000/mm3, and the WBC count is 5820/mm3. Infection with which of the following viruses is most likely to be causally related to the development of these findings?","answers":[{"option":"Epstein-Barr virus","bool":true},{"option":"Cytomegalovirus","bool":false},{"option":"Human papillomavirus","bool":false},{"option":"Hepatitis B virus","bool":false},{"option":"HIV","bool":false}]},{"id":121,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 35-year-old man with a history of intravenous drug abuse has generalized lymphadenopathy. Which of the following tests would help in finding the cause of his lymphadenopathy?","answers":[{"option":"Ultrasonography","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow biopsy","bool":false},{"option":"HIV serology","bool":true},{"option":"Histopathology","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":false}]},{"id":122,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2022","question":"A 70-year-old man has experienced increasing fatigue for the past 6 months. On physical examination, he has non-tender axillary and cervical lymphadenopathy but no hepatosplenomegaly. The CBC shows hemoglobin, 9.5 g/dL; hematocrit, 28%; MCV, 90 μm3; platelet count, 120,000/mm3; and WBC count, 42,000/mm3. His peripheral blood smear shows a monotonous population of small, round, mature-looking lymphocytes. Flow cytometry shows these cells as CD19+, CD5+, CD23-, and deoxynucleotidyl transferase negative (TdT−). Cytogenetic and molecular analysis of the abnormal cells in his blood will most likely reveal which of the following alterations?","answers":[{"option":"Clonal rearrangement of immunoglobulin genes","bool":true},{"option":"t(8;14) leading to c-MYC overexpression","bool":false},{"option":"Clonal rearrangement of T-cell receptor genes","bool":false},{"option":"t(9;22) leading to BCR-ABL rearrangement","bool":false},{"option":"t(14;18) leading to BCL2 overexpression","bool":false}]}]
export default arr